A Guide to the Papers of Lewis Preston Summers 1814-1947
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Lewis Preston Summers 1814-1947
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2781
ca. 20,500 items (50 Hollinger boxes and thirty-three 2M Ledgers, ca. 25 linear shelf feet)
The Papers of Lewis Preston Summers contain correspondence concerning genealogy, Virginia history, and politics; financial and legal records; book notes and manuscripts; photographs; a Ku Klux Klan file; voter lists, diaries, and speeches.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These papers were purchased from Andrew R. Summers, New York City, by the University of Virginia Library on March 15, 1965.
Biographical/Historical Information
Lewis Preston Summers (1868-1943) was the son of John Calhoun and Nannie Montgomery (Preston) Summers. John C. Summers was a captain of the "Monroe Invincibles", Company A, 3rd Virginia Regiment, and major and lieutenant colonel, of the 60th Virginia Infantry. His mother was the daughter of John F. Preston, of Locust Glen, Washington County. Summers graduated from the Wytheville Male Academy (1886), the University of Virginia (1890-1893) in common and statute law, studying with Professor John B. Minor, and Tulane (1894-1895) civil law. He married Annie Katherine Barbee of Giles County, in 1897, and they had Gay White, Jane Douglas, Lewis Preston, Katharine Barbee, John Grant, Andrew Rowan, and Olivia Wirt.
Summers served as a railway postal clerk, on the route between Lynchburg, Virginia, and Bristol, Tennessee, and as the Abingdon postmaster, 1890-1894. He began his legal practice in Abingdon in 1895, was commonwealth attorney for Washington County (1904-1905), collector of internal revenue, Western district of Virginia (1905-1913), and appointed U.S. district attorney, by President Harding, in 1922, and member of the Virginia State Bar Association and Presbyterian Church. He was a member of the Republican district committee from the ninth Virginia district from 1894-1904 and elected a member of the Republican State executive committee on March 1904. Summers was also the chairman of the Walnut Grove Cemetery Association, Washington County, Virginia. The land upon which this historic cemetery was located was originally owned by Robert Preston, Sr. of Walnut Grove, whose wife, Margaret Rhea Preston, and mother, Eleanor Fairman Preston, established the cemetery. Several bound volumes pertaining to Walnut Grove and the Preston family are present in this collection.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of the papers of Lewis Preston Summers (1868-1943), a lawyer, genealogist, member of the Republican Party, and author of Abingdon, Virginia, containing correspondence concerning genealogy, the history of Southwest Virginia, and politics, especially local politics of the ninth Virginia district, Congressman Campbell Bascom Slemp, and applicants for political positions (1870-1943); financial and legal records for the newspaper The Virginia Republican, owned and edited by Summers; genealogical and historical research notes; and setting copies, galleys, page proofs, and drafts, of manuscripts for his books, Annals of Southwest Virginia and History of Southwest Virginia, and the unpublished Southwest Virginia in the World War.
Other materials include photographs; news clippings and printed; World War I History Commission papers, kept by Summers, who was the chairman of the Washington County Virginia War History Commission, including correspondence, military service records of men serving from Southwest Virginia, arranged alphabetically, photographs of soldiers and scenes, and related material; bound volumes, especially several pertaining to the Preston family of Walnut Grove, Washington County; a file on the Ku Klux Klan (Box 22); lists of voters; memorabilia; speeches by Lewis Preston Summers; invitations; the original and typescript copy of the journal of Hugh Johnston (Box 25); land plots; and papers concerning the Walnut Grove Cemetery Association, for the preservation of the historic Walnut Grove Presbyterian Church Cemetery, four miles east of Bristol, Washington County, Virginia (Box 32).
Photographs of men who appear as illustrations in History of Southwest Virginia(see Box 26, Photographs of Distinguished Men of Washington County & Southwest Virginia) include: Charles W. Alderson; David F. Bailey; Charles S. Bekem; Henry Bowen; Rees T. Bowen; B.F. Buchanan; John A. Buchanan; Joseph M. Butt; Joseph T. Campbell; David B. Clark; C.H. Clung; Charles B. Coale; the Rev. Lewis F. Cosby; Judge David C. Cummings; Joseph Draper; David C. Dunn; Samuel P. Edmondson; Benjamin Estill; John B. Floyd; Isaac Chapman Fowler; Colonel Abram Fulkerson; Judge F.V. Fulkerson; Andrew S. Fulton; George Graham; Robert E. Grant; James S. Greever; A.J. Huff; Francis B. Hutton; Charles H. Jennings; John W. Johnston; General William E. Jones; Judge John A. Kelly; E.S. Kendrick; Selden Longley; J.W. Mort; Fayette McMullen; John W. Price; Andrew F. Rambo; James B. Richmond; E.L. Roberts; John Roberts; John P. Sheffey; Campbell Slemp; Alexander Smyth; L.H. Snodgrass; Charles W. Steele; John C. Summers; William Terry; W.H. Tomney; Connally F. Trigg; James A. Walker; George W. Ward, Jr.
Organization
This collection is arranged in seven series:
Series I: Manuscripts of Books by Lewis Preston Summers (Boxes 1-10)
Series II: Correspondence re Genealogy (Boxes 11- 14)
Series III: Papers re The Virginia Republican Newspaper (Boxes 15-16)
Series IV: Political Correspondence & Related Papers (Boxes 16-25)
Series V: Research Notes & Miscellaneous Files (Boxes 25- 32)
Series VI: World War I History Commission Papers (Boxes 32-36)
Series VII: Bound Ledgers, Scrapbooks & Other Volumes (Boxes 37-50, including Ledgers & Oversize Boxes S-49 & M-18)
Contents List
- Manuscripts of Books by Lewis Preston Summers
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia pages 1-1000 1929, 5 folders; setting copy (Box 1)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia, pages 1001-1984 1929, 5 folders; setting copy (Box 2)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia, Author's First Proof 1929, 5 folders; galleys (Box 3)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia, Author's First Proof, pages 1-330 1929 Jun 29, page proof (Box 3)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia, Author's First Proof, pages 331 to the end, including an index 1929 Jun 29, 4 folders; page proof (Box 4)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Miscellaneous Court Records ca. 1929, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Miscellaneous Court Records ca. 1929, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Journal of Dr. Thomas Walker 1929 (Box 6)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Botetourt County 1929, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Fincastle County 1929 (Box 6)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Montgomery County 1929 (Box 6)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Revolutionary Soldiers 1929 (Box 6)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Washington County & Minutes of its County Court 1929, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Wythe County 1929 (Box 6)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Illustrations 1929, galleys; page proofs (Box 7)
  - Annals of Southwest Virginia- Illustrations 1929, photographs (Box 7)
  - History of Southwest Virginia- Outline History of Virginia, Errata, & Introduction 1903, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - History of Southwest Virginia- Chapters 1-6 Fincastle County 1903, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - History of Southwest Virginia- Chapters 6 The Revolution through Chapter 9 1903, 6 folders (Box 8)
  - History of Southwest Virginia- Chapter 10 & Boundaries of Washington County 1903, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - History of Southwest Virginia, numbered with blue pencil, incomplete ca. 1903, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - History of Southwest Virginia- Miscellaneous Drafts [pre 1903], 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Southwest Virginia in World War- Unpublished & Incomplete Typescipt ca. 1947 (Box 10)
- Correspondence re Genealogy
  - Correspondence re the Genealogy and History of Southwest Virginia 1901-1929 Sep, 6 folders (Box 11)
  - Correspondence re the Genealogy and History of Southwest Virginia 1929 Oct-1931 Dec, 6 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence re the Genealogy and History of Southwest Virginia 1932-1938, 7 folders (Box 13)
  - Correspondence re the Genealogy and History of Southwest Virginia 1939-1943, n.d., 7 folders (Box 14)
- Papers re The Virginia Republican Newspaper
  - Financial & Legal Papers - The Virginia Republican 1901-1916, 7 folders (Box 15)
  - Financial & Legal Papers - The Virginia Republican1922-1926, 1938-1942, n.d., 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Financial & Legal Papers - The Virginia Republican- Account Book 1907-1912 (Box 16)
- Political Correspondence & Related Papers
  - Ballots ca. 1914-1936 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence 1901-1905 Mar, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - Correspondence 1905 Apr-Nov, 8 folders (Box 17)
  - Correspondence 1906-1910, 6 folders (Box 18)
  - Correspondence 1911-1913, 7 folders (Box 19)
  - Correspondence 1914-1916, 7 folders (Box 20)
  - Correspondence 1917-1943, n.d., 9 folders (Box 21)
  - County Republican Committee Members ca. 1913-1922 (Box 22)
  - Finances ca. 1905-1924 (Box 22)
  - Ku Klux Klan 1924 (Box 22)
  - Lists of Candidates and Delegates ca. 1905-1917 (Box 22)
  - Lists of Voters 1904, 1907-1920, 5 folders (Box 22)
  - Lists of Voters 1918-1923, n.d., 5 folders (Box 23)
  - Lists of Voters of Washington County 1910, 1 of 5 folders (Box 23)
  - Lists of Voters of Washington County 1910, 4 folders (Box 24)
  - Minutes of Meetins & Reports ca. 1885-1939 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous & Memorabilia ca, 1904-1913 (Box 24)
  - News clippings & Press Releases ca. 1904-1924 (Box 24)
  - Precinct Poll Books ca. 1914-1917 (Box 25)
  - Proxies for Meetings of the Republican County Committee 1912-1914 (Box 25)
  - Speaking Appointments n.d. (Box 25)
  - Voter Registration Forms ca. 1906-1915 (Box 25)
  - Voting Tallies ca. 1849-1916 (Box 25)
- Research Notes & Miscellaneous Files
  - Historical Societies - Papers & Certificates of Membership 1921-1944 (Box 25)
  - Invitations 1915-1938, n.d. (Box 25)
  - Journal of Hugh Johnston & Typescripts of Extracts from his Diary 1866-1867 (Box 25)
  - Letter of Thomas White, Cross Roads, Maryland, to Richard White, Abingdon, Virginia 1814 Nov 15 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous Papers ca. 1909-1938 (Box 25)
  - News clippings re Genealogy & History 1901-1943 (Box 25)
  - Photographs ca. 1890-1915 (Box 26)
  - Photographs of "Distinguished Men of Washington County & Southwest Virginia" [ca. 1903] (Box 26)
  - Postcards n.d. (Box 26)
  - Research Notes n.d. (Box 26)
  - Research Notes re Abingdon, Virginia 1930-1946, n.d., 2 folders (Box 26)
  - Research Notes re Acts of the House of Burgesses n.d. (Box 27)
  - Research Notes re the Battle of Kings Mountain ca. 1938 (Box 27)
  - Research Notes re Biographies 1903, n.d., 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Research Notes re Bristol, Virginia n.d. (Box 27)
  - Research Notes re Civil War n.d. (Box 27)
  - Research Notes re Churches & Religion ca. 1887-1943 (Box 27)
  - Research Notes re Court Records 1937-1938, n.d. (Box 27)
  - Research Notes re Education 1865, 1903, n.d. (Box 28)
  - Research Notes re Executives of Virginia, Representatives, Senators, & Local Officers and Officials n.d. (Box 28)
  - Research Notes re Genealogy 1914-1943, n.d., 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Research Notes re the Judiciary 1909, 1941, n.d. (Box 28)
  - Research Notes re Lawyers of Southwest Virginia n.d. (Box 28)
  - Research Notes re the Local Board for Washington County and Bristol, Virginia, in World War I 1917-1918, n.d. (Box 29)
  - Research Notes re Marriages n.d. (Box 29)
  - Research Notes re Masonic Lodge, Abingdon n.d. (Box 29)
  - Research Notes re Military Officers & Soldiers 1901, n.d. (Box 29)
  - Research Notes re Miscellaneous 1903, n.d., 2 folders (Box 29)
  - Research Notes re Revolutionary Records 1897, 1901, n.d. (Box 29)
  - Research Notes re Speeches by Andrew Moore 1938 (Box 30)
  - Research Notes re Tennessee n.d. (Box 30)
  - Research Notes re Transcripts of Letters concerning Southwest Virginia n.d., 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Research Notes re Virginia Members of the House of Representatives 1901-1936, n.d. (Box 30)
  - Research Notes re Washington County 1901, n.d. (Box 30)
  - Speeches by Lewis Preston Summers 1916-1943, n.d. (Box 30)
  - Speeches by Lewis Preston Summers 1938-1941, n.d. (Box 31)
  - Speeches by Others 1905, 1923 (Box 31)
  - Subscription & Address Lists 1902-1931, n.d., 3 folders (Box 31)
  - Walnut Grove Cemetary Association 1929-1943, n.d. (Box 32)
- World War I History Commission Papers
  - Correspondence ca. 1919-1942, n.d., 3 folders (Box 32)
  - Military Service Records A-B ca. 1917-1922, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Military Service Records C-J ca. 1917-1930, 9 folders (Box 33)
  - Military Service Records K-V ca. 1917-1931, 10 folders (Box 34)
  - Military Service Records W ca. 1921-1922 (Box 35)
  - Papers & Related Material n.d. (Box 35)
  - Photographs of World War I Soldiers & Scenes ca. 1916-1925 (Box 35)
  - Typescripts of Letters from Soldiers to their families during World War I ca. 1918-1919 (Box 35)
  - Southwest Virginia in the World War by Lewis Preston Summers 1931 (Box 36)
    Bound Typescipt with photographs, post cards, and news clippings bound in
- Bound Ledgers, Scrapbooks & Other Volumes
  - Invoice Book of Robert Preston 1794-1806 (Box 37)
  - Daybook 1796 (Box 37)
  - Walnut Grove Daybook 1800-1807 (Box 37)
  - Walnut Grove Ledger, belonging to Robert Preston, with index 1802-1803 (Box 38)
  - Daybook 1805-1832 (Box 38)
  - Invoice Book belonging to Robert Preston 1816-1824 (Box 38)
  - Walnut Grove Daybook, belonging to Robert Preston 1819-1825 (Box 38)
  - Elizabethton Daybooks 1819-1820, 2 volumes (Box 39)
  - Cashbook belonging to John C. Summers 1877-1878 (Box 40)
  - Key & Box Book 1893-1894 (Box 40)
  - Ledger ca. 1894, foldered (Box 40)
  - Scrapbook of News clippings, belonging to Lewis Preston Summers ca. 1897-1918 (Box 40)
  - "Registered Voters with Politics & Address 9th Virginia District" 1904 (Box 41)
  - Subsription Receipt Book 1923-1924 (Box 41)
  - Freight Receipt Book ca. 1903-1904 (Box 42)
  - Virginia Press, Circulation Department Record Book 1904-1905 (Box 42)
  - Rental Contracts & Correspondence re History & Genealogy ca. 1909-1928 (Box 43)
  - Records re Building belonging to Lewis Preston Summers, including Correspondence, Contracts, Receipts & Purchases 1875-1912 (Box 43)
  - Records re Building belonging to Lewis Preston Summers, including Correspondence, Contracts, Receipts & Purchases 1909-1911, 2 volumes (Box 44)
  - Letterbook of Lewis Preston Summers with recommedations for U.S. Attorney (1904) and Nomination as Governor of Virginia (1909) 1904 & 1909 (Box 45)
  - Letterbook of Lewis Preston Summers re Politics & Personal Affairs 1905-1909 (Box 45)
  - Letterbook of Lewis Preston Summers re Politics, History & Genealogy/Political Scrapbook/ and Records re Buildings belonging to Lewis Preston Summers ca. 1893-1915 (Box 46)
  - Scrapbook of News clippings ca. 1880-1904 (Box 46)
  - Letterbook of Lewis Preston Summers re Politics, History & Genealogy ca. 1906-1911 (Box 47)
  - Letterbook of Lewis Preston Summers re Politics, History & Genealogy ca. 1916-1928 (Box 47)
  - Letterbook of Lewis Preston Summers re Politics, History & Genealogy, with index ca. 1909-1929, 1 bound volume (Box 48)
  - Letterbook of Lewis Preston Summers re Politics, History & Genealogy, with index ca. 1909-1929, folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 48)
  - Letterbook of Lewis Preston Summers re Politics, History & Genealogy, with index ca. 1909-1929, folder 3 of 3 (Box 49)
  - Ledger with index, belonging to Lewis Preston Summers ca. 1908-1919 (Box 49)
  - Financial Records of the "Adopted Sons & Daughters of Zion" ca. 1911-1915 (Box 49)
  - Abingdon Publishing Company Ledger, with index ca. 1923-1925 (Box 50)
  - List of Revolutionary Soldiers from Southwest Virginia, compiled by Lewis Preston Summers n.d. (Box 50)
  - Walnut Grove Ledger, with partial index 1804-1805
  - Walnut Grove Ledger 1806-1811
  - Walnut Grove Journal 1811-1819
  - Ledger belonging to Robert Preston 1813-1825
  - Ledger for merchandise 1823-1826
  - Blountville Daybook 1824-1825
  - Ledger for merchandise 1838-1846, damaged
  - Scrapbook ca. 1864-1930
  - Minutes Book of the Republican Congrssional District Committee 9th Virginia District; also a political scrapbook 1883-1912
  - Letter book of Correspondence re Summers' History of Southwest Virginia 1903-1905
  - List of Voters in Giles County - Pearisburg & Walkers Creek Districts 1903-1908
  - List of Voters in Russell County - New Garden, Castlewood, & Copper Creek Districts ca. 1903-1908
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Abingdon District ca. 1904
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Abingdon District ca. 1908-1913
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Glade Spring District ca. 1904
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Glade Spring & Holston Districts 1904-1910
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Goodson District 1902-1910
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Goodson District ca. 1912-1918
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Holston District ca. 1906-1911
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Holston District ca. 1912-1918
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Kinderhook District ca. 1908-1913
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Kinderhook District ca. 1912-1918
  - List of Voters in Washington County - North Fork District ca. 1908-1913
  - List of Voters in Washington County - North Fork District ca. 1912-1918
  - List of Voters in Washington County - North Fork, Goodson, & Kinderhook Districts ca. 1903-1908
  - List of Voters in Washington County - North Fork, Goodson, & Kinderhook Districts 1919-1925
  - List of Voters in Washington County - North Fork, Goodson, & Kinderhook Districts ca. 1923-1929
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Saltville District 1904,1912-1918
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Saltville District 1908-1913
  - List of Voters in Washington County - Saltville, North Fork, & Abingdon Districts 1919-1925
  - Guest Register Book for the Hotel Dagmar, Abingdon, Virginia ca. 1912-1913
  - [Voter Register?] (mostly empty) n.d.
  - List of Voters in Goodson, North Fork, Abingdon, and Kinderhook, Washington County ca. 1907-1925, 2 volumes (Box S-49)
  - 2 Unidentified Plats n.d. (Box M-18)